MARCOS ORTIZ, PHD

970.312.6561 • Grand Junction, CO • marcos.ortiz.math@gmail.com • LinkedIn • gitHub

SUMMARY

I am a PhD Mathematician from the University of Iowa, with more than 14 years of academic and research experience. My research interests include contact topology, and experimental mathematics. I am proficient in programming, machine learning, and data science. I love to explore technical questions and puzzles, and learn about new tools that can be applied to solving these problems. I am currently at a transition point in my career, seeking industry opportunities in data science, machine learning, or related fields.

EXPERIENCE

Colorado Mesa University, Grand Junction, CO

2018 – present

Instructor of Mathematics

- Designed and implemented extensive inquiry based course materials for the Engineering Calculus sequence, as well as Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, and Discrete Mathematics.
- Adapted course material for remote learning in Precalculus, Calculus I, II, and III.
- Earned an overall score of 95% on student evaluations across all courses taught.
- Awarded the highest possible faculty performance rating, *Exceptional*, for the past 4 years in a row.

Grinnell College, Grinnell, IA

2015-2018

Visiting Assistant Professor

- Mentored advanced undergraduate summer research projects in topology and topological data analysis.
- Developed lectures, homework, exams, and student projects for Linear Algebra, Number Theory, Topology, and Abstract Algebra.

University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA

2009-2015

Graduate Fellow

- Conducted graduate research in topology, contact topology, and experimental mathematics
- Proved novel results in contact topology, establishing a classification of a mathematical phenomena under a broad set of hypotheses.
- Organized a graduate research group in topology, which drew speakers from a variety of fields, including contact topology, knot theory, and topological data analysis.

MACHINE LEARNING

Through coursework and certifications I have developed familiarity with many fundamental concepts and machine learning tools, including:

- Using popular machine learning libraries like NumPy, scikit-learn, Tensorflow, and keras
- Building and training supervised machine learning models for prediction and binary classification tasks, including linear regression and logistic regression
- Supervised learning (multiple linear regression, logistic regression, neural networks, and decision trees)
- Unsupervised learning (clustering, dimensionality reduction, recommender systems),
- Best practices for artificial intelligence and machine learning innovation (evaluating and tuning models, taking a data-centric approach to improving performance)

SKILLS AND CERTIFICATES

Mathematics: Research, Topology, Experimental Mathematics, Contact Topology, Topological Data Analysis **Technical:** python, C++, SQL, Excel, LATEX, git

Python Libraries: numpy, pandas, matplotlib, seaborn, tensorflow, keras, scikit-learn, scipy

Deeplearning.AI and Stanford University Certificates: •Machine Learning Specialization •Unsupervised Learning, Recommenders, Reinforcement Learning •Advanced Learning Algorithms •Supervised Machine Learning: Regression and Classification

EDUCATION

PhD, Mathematics University of Iowa Department of Mathematics	2015
Graduate Certificate in College Teaching University of Iowa Graduate College	2014
Masters, Mathematics University of Iowa Department of Mathematics	2012
B.Sc., Mathematics State University of New York at Buffalo Department of Mathematics	2009
B.A. , Psychology University of North Carolina at Wilmington Department of Psychology	2004